<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://smallsheds.garden/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Joep Schuurkes (Posts about black box puzzle)</title>
  <id>https://smallsheds.garden/categories/black-box-puzzle.atom</id>
  <updated>2026-02-14T15:18:24Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://smallsheds.garden/categories/black-box-puzzle.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://smallsheds.garden/categories/black-box-puzzle/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Solving Black Box Puzzle 31 with data analysis</title>
    <id>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2019/solving-black-box-puzzle-31-with-data-analysis/</id>
    <updated>2019-04-28T13:16:34+02:00</updated>
    <published>2019-04-28T13:16:34+02:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2019/solving-black-box-puzzle-31-with-data-analysis/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/workroomprds"&gt;James Lyndsay&lt;/a&gt; has created a number of amazing &lt;a href="http://blackboxpuzzles.workroomprds.com/"&gt;Black Box Puzzles&lt;/a&gt;: tiny applications that challenge you to figure out what they do. (You can support him in creating more of these at &lt;a href="https://www.patreon.com/workroomprds"&gt;his Patreon page&lt;/a&gt;.) Two of these Puzzles, &lt;a href="http://blackboxpuzzles.workroomprds.com/puzzle29/"&gt;29&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://blackboxpuzzles.workroomprds.com/puzzle31/"&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;, not only have a GUI to explore, but also an API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that gave me an idea. If you explore these Puzzles through their GUI, you start from the inputs. You try out different inputs in the hope of discovering a pattern in the outputs. And then that pattern feeds back into your exploration.&lt;br&gt;
With an API, however - and because of the nature of Puzzle 31 - it becomes easy to get the outputs for all possible combinations of inputs. Which means you can start your exploration from the outputs instead of the inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I tell you how and what I did, three important remarks.&lt;br&gt;
First of all, I will be spoiling the solution to the Puzzle in this blog post. So this is the right moment to go and solve &lt;a href="http://blackboxpuzzles.workroomprds.com/puzzle31/"&gt;Puzzle 31&lt;/a&gt; for yourself first. Or at least go play a bit with it, so you have an idea what the inputs and outputs are.&lt;br&gt;
Secondly, I had already solved the Puzzle through the GUI a few months ago. So it was more of a "Can I find the solution this way as well?" than a "Can I find the solution?" thing.&lt;br&gt;
Finally, the code and the spreadsheet I created (linked throughout, also available on GitHub &lt;a href="https://github.com/j19sch/blackbox-puzzle-31"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), are not very clean. I thought about tidying them up, but my two reasons for not doing so are (1) laziness; (2) the way they are now gives a more honest picture of what I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2019/solving-black-box-puzzle-31-with-data-analysis/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (18 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="black-box-puzzle" label="black box puzzle"/>
    <category term="data-analysis" label="data analysis"/>
    <category term="exploratory-testing" label="exploratory testing"/>
    <category term="python" label="python"/>
    <category term="test-automation" label="test automation"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
