<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Joep Schuurkes (Posts about bugs)</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://smallsheds.garden/categories/bugs.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:site@joep.slmail.me"&gt;Joep Schuurkes&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0;margin: 0px 0px 0px 0px" src="https://licensebuttons.net/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 13:46:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A backlog item is a backlog item is a backlog item</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originally Scrum was very much about &lt;em&gt;"You tell us what needs building. We'll decide how we build it and how soon we'll deliver."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I've never seen that version of Scrum. The version I have seen, has a product manager try to get as many features into a sprint as reasonably possible - for varying degrees of reasonable. This comes at the expense of maintenance work, such as keeping libraries up-to-date or removing technical debt. And it incentivizes the team to cut corners on features, to not leave code in a better state than they found it, to not fix smaller bugs and instead log them somewhere for later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution I see to this problem, is to put an engineering manager fully in charge of the team.&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item/#fn:5"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The product manager prioritizes the features. The engineering manager prioritizes the full scope of work for the team. That's not a simple change to pull off, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another solution might be to change the way we use our backlogs. If a product manager gets to prioritize all the work, and the tool they use is a backlog, then we should make sure that all the work&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item/#fn:2"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is in the backlog: features, bugs, and technical debt. Let's take a look at each of these three categories of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>agile</category><category>bugs</category><category>tech debt</category><category>work management</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item-is-a-backlog-item/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 06:51:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Site analytics: if you have two watches...</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2021/site-analytics-if-you-have-two-watches/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I moved my blog to this site, I added &lt;a href="https://clicky.com/"&gt;Clicky&lt;/a&gt; as a privacy-friendly way to collect analytics. About a month ago I added &lt;a href="https://plausible.io/"&gt;Plausible&lt;/a&gt; analytics, because I wanted to compare the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My reasons to consider an alternative to Clicky, and Plausible in particular, were varied. Plausible looks nicer. Clicky's free plan only lets you track one site, I want analytics for this site and for my &lt;a href="https://context-of-agile.org/"&gt;Context of Agile&lt;/a&gt; site. I'd like to have more than 30 days of history for my data. Those last two wishes require a paid plan (regardless if Clicky or Plausible) and Plausible is cheaper than Clicky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I got a 30-day trial with Plausible, added its script to my site, while Clicky also kept collecting data. With the trial now over, it's time to take a look at the data they both collected over the period from 28 November to 27 December 2021. I've added some thoughts after each table with data and at the end of this post I've added some more general thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2021/site-analytics-if-you-have-two-watches/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bugs</category><category>this site</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2021/site-analytics-if-you-have-two-watches/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 10:08:16 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>