<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Joep Schuurkes (Posts about ci/cd)</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://smallsheds.garden/categories/cat_cicd.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:site@joep.slmail.me"&gt;Joep Schuurkes&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons BY-NC License" style="border-width:0;margin: 0px 0px 0px 0px" src="https://licensebuttons.net/l/by-nc/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 14:21:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Not continuous everything!</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2025/not-continuous-everything/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 18 of "Taking Testing Seriously" (I skipped ahead, sue me), &lt;a href="https://qualityremarks.com/"&gt;Keith Klain&lt;/a&gt; says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much today is about "continuous everything" - continuous deployment, continuous integration - and speed. The pace at which people are doing things is really, really disruptive to thinking deeply about problems. Then the goal gets displaced from getting good products and services to customers quickly, and turns into, "How do we back something out quickly when we inevitably screw up?" It's continuous everything - except continuous thinking.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;- Taking Testing Seriously, James Bach, Michael Bolton et al., 2025, p. 424&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has a point. But I got there by first kind of disagreeing with what he said. Because "continuous everything" is not about speed. It's about risk. Or rather, about managing certain risks: the risk of (code) integration and the risks of delivery/deployment. And how fast you go, should not just be determined by those two specific risks. (Or even worse, by the fact that you just think it's really cool that you can release every commit to your users.) It should be determined by your overall risk appetite, which is a much broader perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2025/not-continuous-everything/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ci/cd</category><category>quality engineering</category><category>risk</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2025/not-continuous-everything/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Your CI/CD pipeline does not run regression tests</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2019/your-ci-cd-pipeline-does-not-run-regression-tests/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;CI/CD pipelines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of a CI/CD pipeline is to allow you to deliver small changes in a fast and controlled way. Without any tests in your pipeline you would gain a lot of speed. You'd also lose a lot control, which is why people in general do run tests in their pipeline. The purpose of these tests is to check if that stage of the pipeline meets the minimum level of acceptable quality for that stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, commit stage tests will consist of mostly unit tests, a few integration tests, and even fewer end-to-end tests, because early in the pipeline speed is more important than comprehensiveness. When I commit my changes, I want the results fast enough so that I will wait for them - ready to fix any issue that might occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Regression testing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many definitions of regression testing, as you can read in &lt;a href="https://arborosa.org/2015/07/31/regression-testing/"&gt;Arborosa's blog post on the topic&lt;/a&gt;. I have always defined regression testing along the lines of "testing the parts that weren't impacted by a change to see if they really weren't impacted." (Which is really weird if you start thinking about it: something is regression testing depending on your knowledge of the system and the change.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The tests in your pipeline are regression tests, …&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the tests that run in your pipeline are regression tests. Your commits are small and you have a lot of tests, so most of those will cover parts of the system that shouldn't have been impacted by your changes. So yes, regression tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2019/your-ci-cd-pipeline-does-not-run-regression-tests/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ci/cd</category><category>devops</category><category>regression testing</category><category>semantics</category><category>test automation</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2019/your-ci-cd-pipeline-does-not-run-regression-tests/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2019 21:47:51 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>