<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Joep Schuurkes (Posts about communication)</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://smallsheds.garden/categories/communication.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:site@joep.slmail.me"&gt;Joep Schuurkes&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons BY-NC License" style="border-width:0;margin: 0px 0px 0px 0px" src="https://licensebuttons.net/l/by-nc/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 11:08:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Testing types - beyond definitions</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2025/testing-types-beyond-definitions/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Testing types in software testing are a mess. It's not just &lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2016/regression-testing-it-means-less-than-you-think/"&gt;"regression testing"&lt;/a&gt; that can mean more things than there are people in the room. It's true for basically all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just last week a teammate said &lt;em&gt;"We should also do integration testing."&lt;/em&gt; So I asked &lt;em&gt;"What do you mean by integration testing?"&lt;/em&gt;. And the reply was: &lt;em&gt;"Testing the frontend and backend together using Playwright."&lt;/em&gt; Which made me think &lt;em&gt;"I see what you mean, but I would never call that integration testing."&lt;/em&gt; and made me reply: &lt;em&gt;"Yeah, we should."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typical solution to this problem is to start defining the different testing types. To me, that's just one approach of many to make sense of testing types. So far I've come up with an additional five.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2025/testing-types-beyond-definitions/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>communication</category><category>heuristics</category><category>semantics</category><category>software testing</category><category>test management</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2025/testing-types-beyond-definitions/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Your default response should be a safe one</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2024/your-default-response-should-be-a-safe-one/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his training DVD &lt;em&gt;"&lt;a href="https://edgeworkbooks.com/dvd-ukemi-from-the-ground-up/"&gt;Ukemi from the Ground Up&lt;/a&gt;"&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href="https://edgeworkbooks.com/about-ellis-amdur/"&gt;Ellis Amdur&lt;/a&gt; explains how your default response should be a safe one. In the context of the video it's about what your action should be in response to an Aikido technique like &lt;em&gt;kote gaeshi&lt;/em&gt;: Do you jump and do a breakfall? Or do you roll? The breakfall is the safe option. The roll is the comfortable one, except for the times you should have done the breakfall. Then you break your wrist...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the choice between breakfall and roll is not up to you. &lt;em&gt;Kote gaeshi&lt;/em&gt; is a throw executed through a wrist lock&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2024/your-default-response-should-be-a-safe-one/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and it's up to the person applying the technique what kind of throw it will be. Either they gently apply the wrist lock, guide you to the ground, and you can roll. Or they apply the technique more dynamically and there's no time to roll. In that case you have to jump and turn over your arm to fall safely on your side/back. That's what's called a breakfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine, there's not always a lot of time to think and decide between roll and breakfall. And if there's no time to think, whatever your default response is, that's what your body will do. That's why your default response to &lt;em&gt;kote gaeshi&lt;/em&gt; should be the breakfall, the response that's safe in both circumstances. The worst case scenario is that you take a breakfall you didn't need to. While the alternative, defaulting to the role even when you should have done the breakfall, comes with significantly worse consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2024/your-default-response-should-be-a-safe-one/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>communication</category><category>note-taking</category><category>programming</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2024/your-default-response-should-be-a-safe-one/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tackling test automation in a new language</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2024/tackling-test-automation-in-a-new-language/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;While there's value in learning all the ins-and-outs of one particular language, its ecosystem and its testing libraries, I think there's also a lot of value in having experience in several. Or at least, in two. If you only know one, you don't really know what's essential and what's incidental to the one set of tools you know. You don't know from experience in what ways things could be different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picking up a new language is not trivial though, especially if it's your second one. There will be a lot to learn. You will notice similarities between the new language and the one(s) you already know. Sometimes those similarities will help you, sometimes they will mislead you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it's more than picking up a new language. There are also the testing libraries you will use
and the language's ecosystem (e.g. how to install those libraries&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2024/tackling-test-automation-in-a-new-language/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or how to set up a pre-commit hook with a linter). That's quite a package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2024/tackling-test-automation-in-a-new-language/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>agile</category><category>communication</category><category>programming</category><category>test automation</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2024/tackling-test-automation-in-a-new-language/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>My seven-month experiment of sharing weekly notes at work</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/my-seven-month-experiment-of-sharing-weekly-notes-at-work/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of my first week at my last job I published a Notion page that started with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href="https://agilecommshandbook.com/"&gt;"The agile comms handbook"&lt;/a&gt; I'm experimenting with a &lt;strong&gt;weekly (internal) blog&lt;/strong&gt;. No big promises on the content, just the things I feel like writing about at the end of my week. And as this is an experiment, things might change along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to add a &lt;strong&gt;comment, respond&lt;/strong&gt; to other people's comments and/or &lt;strong&gt;share&lt;/strong&gt; with others!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I'll tell the story of my eight-month experiment with weekly notes. After that, I'll share some tips in case you want to give weekly notes a try too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/my-seven-month-experiment-of-sharing-weekly-notes-at-work/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>agile comms</category><category>books</category><category>communication</category><category>note-taking</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/my-seven-month-experiment-of-sharing-weekly-notes-at-work/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 10:35:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Making meetings work</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/making-meetings-work/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://smallsheds.garden/images/2023/making-meetings-work/venn-meeting.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Too often I've heard people say: &lt;em&gt;"Oh no, not another meeting!"&lt;/em&gt; Usually this means they feel their time at work is split between time in meetings and time in which they do actual work. And to be fair, they have a point. I too have been in plenty of meetings that didn't achieve much of anything. It doesn't have to be this way, however. Meetings can be effective and they can leave you with a real sense of having accomplished something. And in this post I'll explain how to make that happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;We struggle with meetings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="row"&gt;
    &lt;div class="col-md-4"&gt;
        &lt;figure class="figure"&gt;
            &lt;img src="https://smallsheds.garden/images/2023/making-meetings-work/sisyphus-titian.jpg" class="figure-img img-fluid rounded" alt="Sisyphus by Titian"&gt;
            &lt;figcaption class="figure-caption text-center"&gt;Sisyphus by Titian&lt;/figcaption&gt;
        &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="col-md-8"&gt;
            &lt;p style="margin-top:10px"&gt;We struggle with meetings. On the one hand we keep proposing them, scheduling them, attending them. On the other hand we keep complaining about them. We feel sorry for people with a day full of meetings. When a meeting ends early, we &lt;em&gt;"get 10 minutes of our lives back"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;To that &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/j19sch/status/1179798961131012096"&gt;I say&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you feel you do all your work outside of meetings, you're meeting wrong.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;It's something I realized while I was a scrum master: my work happens during meetings. Mostly team meetings and 1-to-1s. There's prep before and follow-up after meetings, but I did the core of my job through meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/making-meetings-work/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (9 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>communication</category><category>facilitation</category><category>leadership</category><category>self-organization</category><category>sociocracy 3.0</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/making-meetings-work/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 07:31:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Metrics, models and conversations</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago someone suggested we should start measuring how many automated test cases versus how many manual test cases we have. Luckily it was part of a longer list of suggested metrics and it was also presented in that way: a list of options, to be discussed later. And the reason I say "luckily" is because I knew I disagreed with using that metric, but didn't have a good explanation as to why. At that moment I could have given a minutes-long monologue about how that metric doesn't fit how I think we should be thinking about testing. However, I have zero expectations that such a monologue could have worked in that situation. It would be all over the place as I philosophize about testing and make all kinds of connections and analogies. A convincing argument that does not make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So since then, I've been thinking: how would I explain my position on measuring manual versus automated test cases? Something to the point, something relatable, something that acknowledges the need behind asking for this metric. And then it hit me: use cooking as an analogy. Now I know plenty of people have made this analogy before. However, I don't remember reading everything I will cover in this post somewhere else. Also, there's value in different people saying similar things, but each in their own voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>communication</category><category>measurements</category><category>metrics</category><category>test automation</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 09:11:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Structuring group discussions with K-cards</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/structuring-group-discussions-with-k-cards/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://smallsheds.garden/images/2022/k-cards/k-cards.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;K-cards are often used at peer conferences to facilitate the discussion after someone has presented their experience report. Some people really hate them. In my experience they're a great tool to enable rich conversations. Since the facilitator uses the K-cards to structure the discussion in threads, K-cards allow the group to drill down to the details of the experience report. This instead of the conversation jumping around as person 1 broaches topic A, person 2 introduces topic B, and person 3 wants to return to topic A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The explanation of these K-cards often takes the form of &lt;em&gt;"This is what each card means."&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;"This is when to use this card for what purpose."&lt;/em&gt; And despite the elegance of the K-cards system, when you learn about them during the opening of a peer conference, it's a lot of information to digest. So I hope this blog post will be useful as a written explanation of how to use K-cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/structuring-group-discussions-with-k-cards/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (8 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>communication</category><category>facilitation</category><category>peer conferences</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/structuring-group-discussions-with-k-cards/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2022 17:27:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Uncovering Agile micro-skills at FroGS conf</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/uncovering-agile-micro-skills-at-frogsconf/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the second &lt;a href="https://frogsconf.nl/"&gt;FroGS conf Open Space&lt;/a&gt; on 12 March 2022 I facilitated a session based on my blog post &lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/four-skills-to-embody-the-four-agile-values/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Four skills to embody the four Agile values"&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. My goal with the session was to uncover more Agile (micro-)skills. In this post I'll share what we did during the session and I'll close off with some thoughts on the biggest challenge of this exercise: too many skills. Before I start however, a big thank you to everyone who participated in the session!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What we value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I opened the session with asking people to add stickies to the board of things they valued in Agile software development. When was I preparing the Miro board before the session, I labeled this part of the board "values". Then I remembered I had decided earlier to label it "what we value", so as to avoid the discussion about what values are and aren't. The topic did come up (i.e. the relation between values, ethics and morals), so I was glad I could respond by saying it's a great topic, but not for this session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/uncovering-agile-micro-skills-at-frogsconf/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>agile</category><category>communication</category><category>conferences</category><category>skills</category><category>values</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/uncovering-agile-micro-skills-at-frogsconf/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 15:56:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Four skills to embody the four Agile values</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/four-skills-to-embody-the-four-agile-values/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you're familiar with the &lt;a href="https://agilemanifesto.org/"&gt;Agile Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, you're familiar with its four values:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Individuals and interactions over processes and tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working software over comprehensive documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer collaboration over contract negotiation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Responding to change over following a plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently this made me wonder: how do you apply these values? How do you live them? What skills do you need to embody them? In this post I won't be sharing any definitive or complete answers, but as a starting point I have identified four skills needed to embody the four Agile values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/four-skills-to-embody-the-four-agile-values/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (9 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>agile</category><category>communication</category><category>skills</category><category>values</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/four-skills-to-embody-the-four-agile-values/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 16:04:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>From tension to agreement with Sociocracy 3.0</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/from-tension-to-agreement-with-sociocracy-30/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month I started my new job at a small consultancy. During my onboarding I noticed something that I thought could be improved. So I figured I should come up with a proposal to address that. It also made me wonder how me proposing this improvement would go over with my new colleagues. And then I remembered I learned about a good way of doing this in a workshop&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/from-tension-to-agreement-with-sociocracy-30/#fn:6"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; at the 2016 &lt;a href="https://xpdaysbenelux.nl/"&gt;XP Days Benelux&lt;/a&gt; conference. That workshop was about &lt;a href="https://sociocracy30.org/"&gt;Sociocracy 3.0&lt;/a&gt; (S3 for short). So I ended up proposing two things in the meeting: my improvement, but also a way to come to an agreement about my proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reactions to my proposal about how to come to agreements, were mostly positive. One person asked a very good question though: &lt;em&gt;"Is this solving a problem we are having? Or is this a solution looking for a problem? What would be the reasons for adopting this?"&lt;/em&gt; In response I expanded on my reasons for wanting this and we decided to give it a try. My dual proposal helped here: let's try the S3 patterns I shared on the improvement I proposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I'm happy with my reply to those questions and I also feel I can do better. Which makes this the perfect opportunity for my first blog post of 2022. I'll start with a brief introduction on Sociocracy 3.0, then I'll share the proposal I made based on S3, and finally I'll talk about why I like this form of decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/from-tension-to-agreement-with-sociocracy-30/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>communication</category><category>heuristics</category><category>leadership</category><category>self-organization</category><category>sociocracy 3.0</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/from-tension-to-agreement-with-sociocracy-30/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 10:27:13 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>