<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://smallsheds.garden/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Joep Schuurkes (Posts about measurements)</title>
  <id>https://smallsheds.garden/categories/measurements.atom</id>
  <updated>2025-07-20T14:52:43Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://smallsheds.garden/categories/measurements.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://smallsheds.garden/categories/measurements/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Metrics, models and conversations</title>
    <id>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/</id>
    <updated>2023-03-12T10:11:25+01:00</updated>
    <published>2023-03-12T10:11:25+01:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago someone suggested we should start measuring how many automated test cases versus how many manual test cases we have. Luckily it was part of a longer list of suggested metrics and it was also presented in that way: a list of options, to be discussed later. And the reason I say "luckily" is because I knew I disagreed with using that metric, but didn't have a good explanation as to why. At that moment I could have given a minutes-long monologue about how that metric doesn't fit how I think we should be thinking about testing. However, I have zero expectations that such a monologue could have worked in that situation. It would be all over the place as I philosophize about testing and make all kinds of connections and analogies. A convincing argument that does not make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So since then, I've been thinking: how would I explain my position on measuring manual versus automated test cases? Something to the point, something relatable, something that acknowledges the need behind asking for this metric. And then it hit me: use cooking as an analogy. Now I know plenty of people have made this analogy before. However, I don't remember reading everything I will cover in this post somewhere else. Also, there's value in different people saying similar things, but each in their own voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="communication" label="communication"/>
    <category term="measurements" label="measurements"/>
    <category term="metrics" label="metrics"/>
    <category term="test-automation" label="test automation"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Measuring review coverage</title>
    <id>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2012/measuring-review-coverage/</id>
    <updated>2012-09-13T19:39:57+02:00</updated>
    <published>2012-09-13T19:39:57+02:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2012/measuring-review-coverage/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently it occurred to me we have plenty of ways to measure test coverage, but there doesn't seem to be a way to measure review coverage. So today I decided to fix that. The result is the scale below with which you can measure review coverage. And just like all good scales, &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XuzpsO4ErOQ"&gt;it goes all the way up to 11&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0) I'm sorry, what document?&lt;br&gt;
1) I think I do remember someone mentioning that document.&lt;br&gt;
2) I'm sure I have it somewhere – well, at least fairly sure...&lt;br&gt;
3) Look, it's on my to do-pile!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2012/measuring-review-coverage/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="coverage" label="coverage"/>
    <category term="measurements" label="measurements"/>
    <category term="reviews" label="reviews"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
