<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://j19sch.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Joep Schuurkes (Posts about slices)</title>
  <id>https://j19sch.github.io/categories/slices.atom</id>
  <updated>2021-11-28T21:06:25Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://j19sch.github.io/categories/slices.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://j19sch.github.io/categories/slices/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>How to run a remote Elephant Carpaccio</title>
    <id>https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2021/how-to-run-a-remote-elephant-carpaccio/</id>
    <updated>2021-11-28T13:35:16+01:00</updated>
    <published>2021-11-28T13:35:16+01:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2021/how-to-run-a-remote-elephant-carpaccio/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href="https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2021/two-times-remote-elephant-carpaccio/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I promised to write a blog post on how I would run remote &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20171114154855/http://alistair.cockburn.us/Elephant+Carpaccio+exercise"&gt;Elephant Carpaccio&lt;/a&gt; if I get the opportunity to run it a third time. This is that post, but not exactly. In the mean time I got the opportunity to run the workshop one more time. That gave me the opportunity to try out some new things and write this blog post on how to run a remote Elephant Carpaccio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should be clear on one thing, though. This post is not a full facilitation guide. It can't be with the limited experience I have. I do hope and think that reading the official(?) &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TCuuu-8Mm14oxsOnlk8DqfZAA1cvtYu9WGv67Yj_sSk/pub"&gt;facilitation guide&lt;/a&gt; and this blog post, gives you a solid base to start running the Elephant Carpaccio exercise remotely yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take your time to prep. Taking &lt;a href="https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2021/lessons-learned-after-facilitating-elephant-carpaccio/#take-your-time-for-the-before-and-after"&gt;as much time as the duration&lt;/a&gt; of the workshop is a good start. (That's assuming you are already familiar with the Elephant Carpaccio exercise, though. So if you're not, do that first.) Get a clear picture in your head what you want to achieve with the workshop. Run through it in your mind in detail. Decide which options you have in which parts of the workshop to make changes as the workshop happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set up all the practical stuff: the invite, the video conferencing link, the virtual whiteboard. How early you do this, depends on how much you expect participants to do before the actual workshop. Since it's a remote workshop my advice is to have them to do as much in advance as possible. I've had good experiences with asking participants to do two things in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2021/how-to-run-a-remote-elephant-carpaccio/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="agile" label="agile"/>
    <category term="elephant-carpaccio" label="elephant carpaccio"/>
    <category term="facilitation" label="facilitation"/>
    <category term="slices" label="slices"/>
    <category term="workshop" label="workshop"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Two times remote Elephant Carpaccio</title>
    <id>https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2021/two-times-remote-elephant-carpaccio/</id>
    <updated>2021-10-03T21:28:50+02:00</updated>
    <published>2021-10-03T21:28:50+02:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2021/two-times-remote-elephant-carpaccio/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A while ago I asked the teams in my department which parts of agile software development they wanted to learn more about. One of the topics that stood out, was: you have a high-level description of a new feature, then what? That's still quite a wide topic, so the question become on what part of that problem would I focus first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite quickly I settled on feature slicing - for several reasons. First of all, I had noticed teams delivering somewhat big chunks of functionality, split up into development tasks instead of vertical slices. Secondly, a team I had worked with on feature slicing, had gained some valuable planning flexibility because of it. And they continued the practice, breaking up projects vertically. Finally, I was aware that there was a workshop called "Elephant Carpaccio", focused on feature slicing. So I could use that, or build on it, but at least I wouldn't have to come up with something from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Elephant Carpaccio exercise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Elephant Carpaccio exercise was invented by Alistair Cockburn&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2021/two-times-remote-elephant-carpaccio/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Its purpose is to get people to practice &lt;em&gt;"nano-incremental"&lt;/em&gt; development, i.e. slicing something small enough you can program it in 15-30 minutes. The exercise tries to bring home its point through exageration: you are asked to slice a very simple application in 15-20 slices, where you would normally do it in 2-3 slices. Then you get five iterations of 8 minutes to build those slices. To me that's the coolest part of the exercise: you actually get to experience what's it like to work with such small slices. As Alistair Cockburn himself says about the exercise: &lt;em&gt;"the true learning is the actual programming section"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2021/two-times-remote-elephant-carpaccio/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="agile" label="agile"/>
    <category term="elephant-carpaccio" label="elephant carpaccio"/>
    <category term="facilitation" label="facilitation"/>
    <category term="slices" label="slices"/>
    <category term="workshop" label="workshop"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
