<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Joep Schuurkes (Posts about tools)</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://smallsheds.garden/categories/tools.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:site@joep.slmail.me"&gt;Joep Schuurkes&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0;margin: 0px 0px 0px 0px" src="https://licensebuttons.net/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 14:52:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Metrics, models and conversations</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago someone suggested we should start measuring how many automated test cases versus how many manual test cases we have. Luckily it was part of a longer list of suggested metrics and it was also presented in that way: a list of options, to be discussed later. And the reason I say "luckily" is because I knew I disagreed with using that metric, but didn't have a good explanation as to why. At that moment I could have given a minutes-long monologue about how that metric doesn't fit how I think we should be thinking about testing. However, I have zero expectations that such a monologue could have worked in that situation. It would be all over the place as I philosophize about testing and make all kinds of connections and analogies. A convincing argument that does not make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So since then, I've been thinking: how would I explain my position on measuring manual versus automated test cases? Something to the point, something relatable, something that acknowledges the need behind asking for this metric. And then it hit me: use cooking as an analogy. Now I know plenty of people have made this analogy before. However, I don't remember reading everything I will cover in this post somewhere else. Also, there's value in different people saying similar things, but each in their own voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>communication</category><category>measurements</category><category>metrics</category><category>test automation</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 09:11:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>My note-taking system for work</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/my-note-taking-system-for-work/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://smallsheds.garden/images/2023/note-taking-system/notebook-and-pen.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ever since I started working back in 2006, I've used a notebook. Initially, I didn't have a system, I just wrote things down. Then, about seven years ago, when I became a scrum master, my notebook became more important. As a tester, I could use my team's board to keep track of my work. As a scrum master, none of my work was on the board. And even though my role has changed several times since then, my need for keeping track of things hasn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So somewhere along the way - and to be honest I forgot when exactly - I created my own system of note-taking based on bullet journaling. It's simple and straightforward. It helps me plan my day, list possible future actions, and keep a record of what I've been doing. On the one hand it seems like something small and simple. On the other hand it has been a major help to me, so I figured it's worth sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/my-note-taking-system-for-work/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (8 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>note-taking</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/my-note-taking-system-for-work/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 14:39:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Our work management tools are limiting our imagination</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/our-work-management-tools-are-limiting-our-imagination/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://smallsheds.garden/images/2023/work-mgt-tools/fig4-stories-on-a-wall.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several weeks ago I had a thought that felt both serious and not serious, so &lt;a href="https://chaos.social/@joeposaurus/109635747014542350"&gt;I asked on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I write a blog post about companies leaving money on the table by not leveraging their choice of work management tool (Jira, Shortcut, etc) as a competitive advantage?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;31% said "yes" and 54% said "a post about what now?", which I suppose reflects my own feelings about the topic. And it motivated me to write this post - especially that 54%. So let's talk about work management tools, the original (user) stories, affordances and constraints, and how these tools are limiting our imagination. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/our-work-management-tools-are-limiting-our-imagination/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (11 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>agile</category><category>agile manifesto</category><category>quality engineering</category><category>software development</category><category>tools</category><category>work management</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/our-work-management-tools-are-limiting-our-imagination/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 21:34:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>It's time to retire our test case management tools</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2020/its-time-to-retire-our-test-case-management-tools/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently the topic of test case management tools popped up a few times in my surroundings. In almost all cases I'd recommend against using these kinds of tools and I found myself able to give a few reasons, but also found that my thoughts lacked the clarity I'd like them to have. Hence this blog post, to force myself to think more deeply and communicate more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I go into that, there are a few things this blog post is not about. I won't be really going into what effect test cases have on test execution, or rather if test cases are a good tool to use when doing actual testing. Personally I don't think they are and I wrote about my inability to use them in &lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2013/test-cases-cant-do-m-no-more/"&gt;this post from July 2013&lt;/a&gt;. For some deeper thoughts on this, I recommend James Bach's and Aaron Hodder's article "&lt;a href="https://www.testingcircus.com/documents/TestingTrapeze-2014-February.pdf#page=31"&gt;Test cases are not testing: Towards a culture of test performance&lt;/a&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I do want to cover in this post is managing test cases. Having a collection of test cases stored somewhere to re-use across releases and reporting their pass/fail numbers. Both are important use cases for a test case management tool and both are in my opinion a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2020/its-time-to-retire-our-test-case-management-tools/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (12 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>heuristics</category><category>test cases</category><category>test management</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2020/its-time-to-retire-our-test-case-management-tools/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 14:38:17 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>