<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://j19sch.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Joep Schuurkes (Posts about tools)</title>
  <id>https://j19sch.github.io/categories/tools.atom</id>
  <updated>2021-04-05T08:24:15Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://j19sch.github.io/categories/tools.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://j19sch.github.io/categories/tools/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>It's time to retire our test case management tools</title>
    <id>https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2020/its-time-to-retire-our-test-case-management-tools/</id>
    <updated>2020-07-19T16:38:17+02:00</updated>
    <published>2020-07-19T16:38:17+02:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Joep Schuurkes</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2020/its-time-to-retire-our-test-case-management-tools/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently the topic of test case management tools popped up a few times in my surroundings. In almost all cases I'd recommend against using these kinds of tools and I found myself able to give a few reasons, but also found that my thoughts lacked the clarity I'd like them to have. Hence this blog post, to force myself to think more deeply and communicate more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I go into that, there are a few things this blog post is not about. I won't be really going into what effect test cases have on test execution, or rather if test cases are a good tool to use when doing actual testing. Personally I don't think they are and I wrote about my inability to use them in &lt;a href="https://testingcurve.wordpress.com/2013/07/06/test-cases-cant-do-m-no-more/"&gt;this post from July 2013&lt;/a&gt;. For some deeper thoughts on this, I recommend James Bach's and Aaron Hodder's article "&lt;a href="https://www.testingcircus.com/documents/TestingTrapeze-2014-February.pdf#page=31"&gt;Test cases are not testing: Towards a culture of test performance&lt;/a&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I do want to cover in this post is managing test cases. Having a collection of test cases stored somewhere to re-use across releases and reporting their pass/fail numbers. Both are important use cases for a test case management tool and both are in my opinion a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://j19sch.github.io/blog/2020/its-time-to-retire-our-test-case-management-tools/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (12 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="test-cases" label="test cases"/>
    <category term="test-management" label="test management"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
