<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Joep Schuurkes</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/</link><description>Joep Schuurkes</description><atom:link href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:site@joep.slmail.me"&gt;Joep Schuurkes&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0;margin: 0px 0px 0px 0px" src="https://licensebuttons.net/l/by/4.0/80x15.png" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 09:41:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Metrics, models and conversations</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago someone suggested we should start measuring how many automated test cases versus how many manual test cases we have. Luckily it was part of a longer list of suggested metrics and it was also presented in that way: a list of options, to be discussed later. And the reason I say "luckily" is because I knew I disagreed with using that metric, but didn't have a good explanation as to why. At that moment I could have given a minutes-long monologue about how that metric doesn't fit how I think we should be thinking about testing. However, I have zero expectations that such a monologue could have worked in that situation. It would be all over the place as I philosophize about testing and make all kinds of connections and analogies. A convincing argument that does not make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So since then, I've been thinking: how would I explain my position on measuring manual versus automated test cases? Something to the point, something relatable, something that acknowledges the need behind asking for this metric. And then it hit me: use cooking as an analogy. Now I know plenty of people have made this analogy before. However, I don't remember reading everything I will cover in this post somewhere else. Also, there's value in different people saying similar things, but each in their own voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>measurements</category><category>metrics</category><category>test automation</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/metrics-models-and-conversations/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 09:11:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>My note-taking system for work</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/my-note-taking-system-for-work/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://smallsheds.garden/images/2023/note-taking-system/notebook-and-pen.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ever since I started working back in 2006, I've used a notebook. Initially, I didn't have a system, I just wrote things down. Then, about seven years ago, when I became a scrum master, my notebook became more important. As a tester, I could use my team's board to keep track of my work. As a scrum master, none of my work was on the board. And even though my role has changed several times since then, my need for keeping track of things hasn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So somewhere along the way - and to be honest I forgot when exactly - I created my own system of note-taking based on bullet journaling. It's simple and straightforward. It helps me plan my day, list possible future actions, and keep a record of what I've been doing. On the one hand it seems like something small and simple. On the other hand it has been a major help to me, so I figured it's worth sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/my-note-taking-system-for-work/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (8 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>note-taking</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/my-note-taking-system-for-work/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 14:39:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Our work management tools are limiting our imagination</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/our-work-management-tools-are-limiting-our-imagination/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://smallsheds.garden/images/2023/work-mgt-tools/fig4-stories-on-a-wall.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several weeks ago I had a thought that felt both serious and not serious, so &lt;a href="https://chaos.social/@joeposaurus/109635747014542350"&gt;I asked on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I write a blog post about companies leaving money on the table by not leveraging their choice of work management tool (Jira, Shortcut, etc) as a competitive advantage?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;31% said "yes" and 54% said "a post about what now?", which I suppose reflects my own feelings about the topic. And it motivated me to write this post - especially that 54%. So let's talk about work management tools, the original (user) stories, affordances and constraints, and how these tools are limiting our imagination. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/our-work-management-tools-are-limiting-our-imagination/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (11 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>agile</category><category>agile manifesto</category><category>quality engineering</category><category>software development</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2023/our-work-management-tools-are-limiting-our-imagination/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 21:34:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>(clj 11) Moving on from some unsolved exercises</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/clojure/2022/clj-11-moving-on-from-some-unsolved-exercises/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of chapter 4 of &lt;a href="https://www.braveclojure.com/clojure-for-the-brave-and-true/"&gt;"Clojure for the Brave and True"&lt;/a&gt; there are &lt;a href="https://www.braveclojure.com/core-functions-in-depth/#Exercises"&gt;four exercises&lt;/a&gt;. This post is about me deciding to move on to chapter 5 after solving 1.5 of these exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The challenge with these exercises&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example to talk about the challenge with these exercises is the second one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a function, append, which will append a new suspect to your list of suspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/clojure/2022/clj-11-moving-on-from-some-unsolved-exercises/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>brave clojure</category><category>clojure</category><category>programming</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/clojure/2022/clj-11-moving-on-from-some-unsolved-exercises/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 15:08:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Three lessons after three months of quality engineering</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/three-lessons-after-three-months-of-quality-engineering/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three months ago I started a new job as a quality engineer, supporting two teams. So far it's been an interesting challenge. The two teams were formed only a few months before I joined, although some team members had been working for the company before that. Each team has their own product manager. We also have an engineering manager, but he joined only two weeks before I did. And then I was added to the mix, with a job description that didn't give a lot more guidance than: support the team in things related to testing and quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my first task in my new job was figuring out what my job was. Or rather, figure out what concrete things I could do that fit that job description. This was not made easier by the fact that we're a fully remote company. Not being in the same space throughout the day does make things harder when you're trying to find your place. Reflecting on the past three months made me realize there are three things that are really important: visibility, connections, and patience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/three-lessons-after-three-months-of-quality-engineering/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>quality engineering</category><category>skills</category><category>small steps</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/three-lessons-after-three-months-of-quality-engineering/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2022 15:41:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Agile tester or quality engineer, who's to say?</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/agile-tester-or-quality-engineer-whos-to-say/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In her article &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20041001003124/http://www.qualitytree.com/feature/btwq.pdf"&gt;"Better Testing, Worse Quality?"&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://ruby.social/@testobsessed"&gt;Elisabeth Hendrickson&lt;/a&gt; makes an interesting case about independent testing, i.e. testing done by an independent test team. She discovered that beyond a certain point, investigating more in independent testing will make both quality and speed go down, not up. In &lt;a href="https://itrevolution.com/podcast/the-idealcast-episode-3/"&gt;episode 3&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href="https://itrevolution.com/podcast/"&gt;Idealcast&lt;/a&gt;, she summarizes her article as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"[...] when you ramp up the amount of investment in an independent test group, then given the amount of pressure that's already on the developers to deliver, it is so easy&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/agile-tester-or-quality-engineer-whos-to-say/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for the developers to say, this isn't my problem anymore. Thank goodness we've got the professionals over here. It's their job to test." &lt;em&gt;(00:11:21)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the article, Elisabeth Hendrickson gives advice on how to avoid or escape this spiral of decreasing quality and speed. There are four dials you can turn either up or down:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/agile-tester-or-quality-engineer-whos-to-say/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>agile</category><category>quality engineering</category><category>software testing</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/agile-tester-or-quality-engineer-whos-to-say/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2022 15:29:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Quality: different purposes, different definitions</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/quality-different-purposes-different-definitions/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;For years when asked to define quality, I've said "value to a person who matters"&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/quality-different-purposes-different-definitions/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Not too long ago I used that definition in the &lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2021/choosing-your-value-system/"&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt; of my four-part series "Thinking about quality". However, in the &lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2021/thinking-about-quality-so-what-to-do/"&gt;fourth post&lt;/a&gt; of that series I also said that quality is something emergent. And I continued with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can have long discussions about what quality is, but that's a different question from how do you get quality?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I took this one step further, when I realized that depending on the context, I talk very differently about quality. And while I may not define 'quality' explicitly in every conversation, implicitly I'm still using different definitions. That alone, I think is interesting: instead of a single, general definition of quality that always applies, I have different definitions depending on their purpose&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/quality-different-purposes-different-definitions/#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/quality-different-purposes-different-definitions/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>quality</category><category>quality engineering</category><category>semantics</category><category>software development</category><category>software testing</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/quality-different-purposes-different-definitions/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 17:41:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Agile Manifesto is a poor introduction to Agile</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/the-agile-manifesto-is-a-poor-introduction-to-agile/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ezagroba"&gt;Elizabeth Zagroba&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ezagroba/status/1557608861690912772"&gt;asked on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone was completely new to working on software on an Agile team, what would you want them to read about Agile first?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first thought was: "The Agile Manifesto!" After a second thought, though, I reconsidered and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/j19sch/status/1557650105930579968"&gt;replied&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I would recommend against reading the Agile Manifesto without consulting any secondary sources, except if you read it in the same way as you would visit a historical site "just to see where it all happened".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I wrote this, I could not really put my finger on why exactly I felt this way. The best I could come up with was that the Agile Manifesto is hard to understand on its own. You need some historical context and practical experience to make sense of it. Serendipity came to the rescue, though, as I'm currently reading &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seeing_Like_a_State"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seeing Like a State&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_C._Scott"&gt;James C. Scott&lt;/a&gt;. Chapter 9 of the book focuses on the Greek concept of &lt;em&gt;mētis&lt;/em&gt; (μῆτις) and how it relates to rules of thumb. Turns out that this explains why the Agile Manifesto is a poor introduction to Agile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/the-agile-manifesto-is-a-poor-introduction-to-agile/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>agile</category><category>agile manifesto</category><category>mētis</category><category>teaching</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/the-agile-manifesto-is-a-poor-introduction-to-agile/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 07:37:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>"Tester" is an overloaded variable</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/tester-is-an-overloaded-variable/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I came across a post on LinkedIn explaining why there are no testers in Scrum&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/tester-is-an-overloaded-variable/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. What struck me most about the post was the amount of work the word "tester" was doing. In one sentence it meant one thing (a role in a team), in the next sentence something else (a step in the process), and so on. Hence the title of this post: the word "tester" was being used as an overloaded variable. So let's do some unpacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Testers to people management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Having a tester"&lt;/em&gt; means that there are people with the official title of "tester" or "QA engineer" or whatever within the company. For the purposes of people management&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/tester-is-an-overloaded-variable/#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, there's a distinction between this role and the other roles in the company. This allows for more specific expectations about the role, for different career paths and salary scales, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/tester-is-an-overloaded-variable/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>management</category><category>semantics</category><category>software testing</category><category>test management</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/tester-is-an-overloaded-variable/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 09:39:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Three thoughts on risk-based testing</title><link>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/three-thoughts-on-risk-based-testing/</link><dc:creator>Joep Schuurkes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The past month I've been thinking about risk-based testing. This post collects three thoughts on risk-based testing I kept returning to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;If not based on risks, then based on what?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a month ago I &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/j19sch/status/1533760354647523330"&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the alternatives to risk-based testing?&lt;br&gt;
Requirements-based? I'd argue that's a subset of risk-based.&lt;br&gt;
Unguided? That's either a bad idea ("we hope to get lucky") or aimed at the risk of unknown unknowns.&lt;br&gt;
Any other options? Because something about the term is bothering me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My question was inspired by the &lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/slides/rtc2019-testing-types.html#/15/0/1"&gt;"opposite" heuristic&lt;/a&gt; from my talk about &lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/slides/rtc2019-testing-types.html#/"&gt;testing types&lt;/a&gt;: if we have some kind of category, what's the name for the things not in that category? Applied to risk-based testing: what's the name for testing that's not risk-based?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/three-thoughts-on-risk-based-testing/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>coverage</category><category>software testing</category><category>test management</category><category>test strategy</category><guid>https://smallsheds.garden/blog/2022/three-thoughts-on-risk-based-testing/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 09:56:30 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>